Guide to the Robert Fitch Papers WAG.261
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Fitch Papers
1905-2016
1990-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fitch, Robert, 1938-
LaTour, Jane
WAG.261
23.75 Linear Feet in 23 record cartons, 1 manuscript box, and 1 half manuscript box
Robert Fitch was an independent journalist, labor union organizer and professor of political sociology, urban studies and labor studies. He is the author of Ghana: End of An Illusion, Who Rules The Corporation?, The Assassination of New York and Solidarity for Sale as well as numerous articles in the Village Voice, the Nation, The Baffler, Newsday, Tikkun and other journals, magazines and newspapers. His books and articles largely focus on corruption within labor unions and local government in New York City. Fitch also taught and lectured at universities throughout New York City, including Long Island University, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, Queens College and LaGuardia Community College. The bulk of the collection consists of Fitch's research files on a variety of topics, including labor union corruption (particularly in relation to real estate deals and pension funds), political corruption, antisemitism, the development and government of New York City, and the history of labor unions. Also included are Fitch's handwritten notebooks and notecards, his speeches and writings are also present, lectures and syllabi from classes he taught at various institutions, cassette tapes containing copies of Fitch's show on WBAI-FM, optical media and a small amount of personal material.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into seven series: I: Subject Files, II: Writings, III: Speeches, IV: Personal Material, V: Cassette Tapes, VI: 2015 Accretion, and VII. 2016 Accretion.
Folders are arranged chronologically within each series.
Accretions to the collection added as Series VI and VII are arranged in the order in which they were received by the donor.
Biographical Note
Robert Fitch was an independent journalist, labor union organizer and professor of political sociology, urban studies and labor studies. Born in December 1938 in Chicago, Fitch joined the Laborers' International Union of North America (LIUNA) Local 5 at the age of 15 as a Laborer.
Fitch attended the University of Illinois, where he earned his Bachelors degree in History. After service in the Air Force, where he worked in military intelligence, Fitch enrolled in the University of California at Berkeley. While earning his Masters in History, he helped to found the Revolutionary Union (which later became the Revolutionary Communist Party) with Bob Avakian, H. Bruce Franklin and Stephen Charles Hamilton. During this period, he also served as the editor of Ramparts, and co-founded the magazine Socialist Revolution, which later became Socialist Review, and then Radical Society.
Fitch co-authored Ghana: End of An Illusion with his wife Mary Oppenheimer, while he was at Berkeley. Published in 1968, the book describes the events leading up to the 1966 overthrow of the Kwame Nkrumah regime. A second book, Who Rules The Corporation? was published in Japanese in 1978. In 1976, Fitch enrolled in the doctoral program of Sociology at the State University of New York at Binghamton. He received his Ph.D. in 1993, after completing his dissertation The Political Economy of New York City: Space, Class and Power, 1958-1992.
In 1980, Fitch began his career as a teacher, serving as an instructor at the Harry Van Arsdale Jr. Center for Labor Studies at Empire State College (Saratoga Springs, NY), where he would teach until 1985. He also began to teach in New York University's Metropolitan Studies Department in 1981. In 1984, he was invited to be a Visiting Critic at Harvard University's Graduate School for Design. In 1985, he was offered a position as a Visiting Professor at the Graduate School of Business at Chuo University's (Tokyo).
After returning to the United States, Fitch returned for a short period to the Metropolitan Studies Department at New York University in 1988. He also worked as an organizer for the American Federation of Musicians, Local 802 in New York City from 1989 to 1990 as well as an adviser to the Communications Workers of America (CWA), Local 1180.
Throughout the 1990s, he worked as a journalist, writing extensively for the Village Voice, the Nation, The Baffler, Newsday, Tikkun and other journals, magazines and newspapers. His articles from this period focus on corruption within labor unions, including election fraud, embezzlement of benefit funds and sweatshop conditions sanctioned by labor unions. In addition, he also pointed out corruption in local government, and the acquiescence of both government and labor to what he termed FIRE; finance, insurance and real estate interests, both on a local and national level. Many of these articles drew the ire of labor union officials and members, particularly those implicated by Fitch's exposes. His book The Assassination of New York, which expanded on these themes, was published by Verso in 1996.
During this time, Fitch also taught and lectured at universities throughout New York City, including Long Island University, John Jay College of Criminal Justice, Queens College and LaGuardia Community College (1993-2011).
In 2006, Public Affairs published his book Solidarity for Sale, which focused on union corruption, which Fitch argued had been a part of organized labor in the United States from its beginnings.
Fitch died at the age of 72 in March 2011.
Scope and Content Note
The bulk of the Robert Fitch Papers consists of journalist, activist, union organizer, and professor Robert Fitch's research files on a variety of topics, including labor union corruption (particularly in relation to real estate deals and pension funds), political corruption, antisemitism, the development of New York City's government, and the history of labor unions. Also included in the collection are Fitch's handwritten notebooks and notecards, interviews he conducted, lectures and syllabi from classes he taught at various institutions, and some of his speeches and writings, including both drafts and published articles. Additionally, a small number of cassette tapes contain recordings of Crossing Wall Street, Fitch's show on WBAI-FM, as well as interviews he conducted with labor union members. There is also a small amount of personal material present in the collection, including correspondence, clippings, certificates and diplomas, files about Fitch's mother Jo, and profiles and tributes largely written after Fitch's passing in 2011.
Related Archival Material
AFSCME, District Council 37 Records (WAG 265) Burton Hall Union Democracy Oral History Project (OH 034) Carpenters for a Stronger Union Records (WAG 066) Kenneth Crowe Papers (WAG 088) Burton Hall Papers (WAG 087) International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Local 282, FORE (Fear of Reprisal Ends) Records (WAG 107) Jane LaTour Papers (WAG 317) James McNamara Papers (WAG 129) United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America, Local 1456 Records (WAG 018)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Robert Fitch in 2006. The accession number associated with this gift is 2006.063.
Jane Latour sent an additional 3 boxes of Robert Fitch's papers in 2011. The accession numbers associated with this gift include 2011.028, 2011.124, and 2011.145.
In October 2015, Jane Latour also sent an additional 4 boxes of Robert Fitch's papers. The accession number associated with this gift is 2015.067.
In 2016, another accretion of two boxes was received by the university from Jane Latour. The accession number assigned to this gift is 2016.052.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu, (212) 998-2630 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Labor unions -- New York (State) -- New York.; Labor unions -- Corrupt practices -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clippings files.; Audiocassettes.; Clothing workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Organized crime |z New York (State); Clothing workers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Political corruption.; Antisemitism.; Research notes.; Pension trusts.; Service Employees International Union; Stern, Andy, 1950-; International Brotherhood of Teamsters; AFSCME. District Council 37 (New York, N.Y.); Teamsters for a Democratic Union; Fitch, Robert, 1938-; International Brotherhood of Painters and Allied Trades; Hotel Employees & Restaurant Employees International Union; International Longshore and Warehouse Union; International Longshoremen's Association; United Association of Journeymen and Apprentices of the Plumbing and Pipe Fitting Industry. Plumbers Local 2 (Manhattan); United Food and Commercial Workers International Union. Local 342-50 (New York, N.Y.); United Brotherhood of Carpenters and Joiners of America; Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees; Mason Tenders District Council of Greater New York; Laborers' International Union of North America; LaTour, Jane; Meany, George, 1894-1980; Fitch, Robert, 1938-; LaTour, Jane
- Series I: Subject Files
  Scope and Content Note
  Contains Fitch's research files on a variety of topics. Although the majority of these files consist of material on labor unions, including District Council 37 (DC37) of the American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), the International Brotherhood of Teamsters (IBT), the Laborers' International Union of North America (LIUNA), Service Employees International Union (SEIU) and the Union of Needletrades, Industrial, and Textile Employees (UNITE), a wide range of subjects, including political corruption, antisemitism, the development and government of New York City and corruption in nonprofit organizations is also included. These files contain news articles, newsletters, bibliographic references, Fitch's typed notes, primary source materials such as annual financial reports for labor unions and their benefit funds, and printed versions of email correspondence and online forums. Fitch's handwritten notebooks and notecards, which document his research, interviews he conducted, and the development of his ideas, are also included in this series, as are lectures and syllabi from classes he taught.
  - Adjunct Faculty, 2004-2006 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aircraft Mechanics Fraternal Association (AMFA), 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Aircraft Mechanics Fraternal Association (AMFA), 1995-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America (AMCBW): Max Block, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Amalgamated Meat Cutters and Butcher Workmen of North America (AMCBW): Packinghouse Strike, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO): Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) Connections, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO): Las Vegas Day Care Workers, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - American Federation of Labor and Congress of Industrial Organizations (AFL-CIO): Merger, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - American Federation of Musicians (AFM): Local 802, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME), 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Annual Report, 1998 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Beverly Rollings-King, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Bonding, 1999-2000 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): Kroll Report, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): National Convention, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (AFSCME): National Taxpayers Union: Policy Paper, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - American Federation of Teachers (AFT): Miami, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - American Federation of Teachers (AFT): Washington, D.C., 2003 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Anti Semitism, 1981-2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Anti Semitism, 1982-2005 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Anti Semitism, 1996-2005 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Anti Semitism, 1997-2005 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Anti Semitism, 2002-2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Anti Semitism: Bibliography, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Articles and Books: Bambrick, James J.: "The Building Service Story", undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Articles and Books: Belser, Michael H.: "Government Oversight, Union Democracy, and Labor Racketeering: Lessons from the Teamsters Experience", 1999 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Articles and Books: Cohen, Andrew Wender, 1998, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Articles and Books: Farber, Henry S. and Bruce Western: "The Decline of Unions in the Private Sector, 1973-1998", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Articles and Books: Foster, William Z.: "Wrecking the Labor Banks", undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Articles and Books: Hill, Herbert, 1963-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Articles and Books: Horowitz, Carl F., 1999, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Articles and Books: Jacobs, James B., Eileen M. Cunningham and Kimberly Friday: "The RICO Trusteeships After Twenty Years: A Progress Report", 2004 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Articles and Books: Latour, Jane, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Articles and Books: Luskin, Robert D.: "Behold the Day of Judgment: Is the RICO Pattern Requirement Void for Vagueness", 1999 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Articles and Books: Moroney, Michael: "Union Corruption and Campaign Contributions", 2000 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Articles and Books: Seidman, Harold: "Labor Czars", 1938 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Articles and Books: Taft, Philip, 1959, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Articles and Books: Velic, Lester, 1959, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Articles and Books: Wellman, David: "The Union Makes Us Strong", 1995 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Articles and Books: Witwer, David: "Corruption and Reform in the Teamsters Union" Chapters 1-6, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Articles and Books: Witwer, David: "Corruption and Reform in the Teamsters Union" Chapters 7-10, 1994 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (BLE), 1925, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (BLE): Venice, Florida`, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (BLE): Warren S. Stone, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Building Trades, 1991-2000 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Class Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Class Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Class Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Class Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Class Lectures, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Class Syllabi, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Construction Firms: New York, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Democratic Socialist of America (DSA), 2009 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Department of Labor Office of Inspector General: Reports, 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1987-2002 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1995-2001 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1996-2000 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1997-2002 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1998-1999 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1998-2000 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1998-2005 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1998-2005 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37), 1999 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Alfred Diop and Martin Lubin Trial, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Alfred Diop and Martin Lubin Trial, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Alfred Diop and Martin Lubin Trial, 2000 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Annual Reports (Form LM-2), 1996-1998 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Barbara Deinhardt (attorney), 2002-2003 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Clippings, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Committee for Real Change in DC37 (CRC), 1999, undated (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Court Cases, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Court Cases, 1995-1999 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Delegate Assembly, 1999 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Directory, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Elections, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Elections, 2000-2002 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Footnotes, 2001-2005 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Funds, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Funds, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Gerald W. McEntee (AFSCME President), 2000 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Goldstein Outline, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Harper, et al v. Roberts and Gray: Arbitration, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Health Benefits: Prescription Drugs, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Helen Greene (Local 768 President), 1999-2001 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): History, 2002, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Book 1), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Book 1), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Book 2), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Book 2), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Book 3), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Book 3), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): KPMG Report (Summary), 2001 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Lillian Roberts, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 299, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 372, 1998-1999 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 375, 1982-2000 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 375, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 375, 1997-1999 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 375, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 384, 1991-1998 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 957, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 983, 1996-1999 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Local 1549, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Materials from Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives, 1980-1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Mike Gimbel, 1994-2000 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): New York Metro Labor Communications Association Speech, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Notes, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Office of Labor Relations Freedom of Information Act (FOIA) Request, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Organized Crime Ties, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - District Council 37, American Federation of State, County and Municipal Employees (DC37): Racketeer Influenced and Corrupt Organizations Act (RICO) Suit, 1999 (Box 3, Folder 37)